Guide to the John R. Williams Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John R. Williams papers
1966-1977
MS 1398
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
14
(34 boxes)
The papers consist of photocopies of correspondence, memoranda, clippings, printed material, transcripts of telephone conversations, and other declassified material from the national headquarters and New Haven, Connecticut office of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, pertaining to the New Haven Chapter of the Black Panther Party. The papers document the investigation of the 1969 murder of Alex Rackley, the subsequent arrests of Bobby Seale and other party members, the surveillance of various demonstrations and protests, particularly those relating to May Day, 1970, and the 1971 trials of Seale and Erika Huggins.
Williams, John R.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. F.B.I. Headquarters Files, 1966-1977. II. F.B.I. New Haven Office Files, 1966-1977.
Biographical / Historical
John R. Williams is an attoreny who started his legal career in 1967 as a lobbyist for Aetna Life & Casualty in Hartford, Connecticut. Disillusioned by his time working in corproate law, Williams left Aetna in 1969 and joined the Hill Neighborhood Law Office of the New Haven Legal Assistance Association as its chief criminal attorney. His first major case was as one of the defense attorneys in the New Haven Black Panther murder trials. Following the acquittal of the so-called "New Haven Nine" in 1971, Williams joined Catherine Roraback and Michael Avery, two other Black Panther Party lawyers, to form New Haven's first public interest law firm. That firm still exists today as John R. Williams and Associates, LLC. Throughout his career, Williams has been best known for his work in the areas of police misconduct litigation, criminal defense, and jury selection reform.
Scope and Contents
The John R. Williams Papers consist of photocopies of Federal Bureau of Investigation (F.B.I.) files concerning the activities of the Black Panther Party in New Haven, Connecticut. The photocopied materials include correspondence, memoranda, informants' reports, transcripts of phone conversations, clippings, photographs, printed material, and other papers from Black Panther Party files at the F.B.I. headquarters in Washington, D.C. and the New Haven, Connecticut office of the bureau. Williams, an attorney for several New Haven area Black Panther Party members, learned that his phone conversations with clients were recorded by the F.B.I. during the late 1960s and early 1970s. He obtained declassified material from these files in 1981 and donated the material to Yale University Library in 1984.
Prior to their release, the files were sanitized to remove information the Justice Department deemed sensitive, including the names of individuals involved in the F.B.I. investigation. These files contain background information beginning in 1966, although the bulk of material follows from the May, 1969 murder of New Haven Black Panther Party member Alex Rackley and the subsequent arrest of party members, including Bobby Seale, the national chairman to the party, on charges of murder and conspiracy to commit murder.
The files document many developments of the trial and the activities of party members. Although Warren Kimbro pleaded guilty to the second degree murder of Alex Rackley in January, 1970, the legal case against a group known as the "New Haven 9" continued. The files detail the surveillance of party members and their counsel, and include reports on movements and activities, party publications, and other documents. The threat of a violent May Day rally in 1970, and the roles of Doug Miranda, captain of the New Haven Black Panthers, and the Yale faculty, administration, and students in maintaining civil order are also documented.
The August, 1970 conviction of Lonnie McLucas, on charges of conspiracy to commit murder, and the trials of Bobby Seale and Erika Huggins in November, 1970 are documented through press and media reports. The activities of defense attorney Charles R. Garry and the court proceedings are also detailed. The trial of Seale and Huggins ended in May, 1971 when the jury was unable to reach a verdict. The F.B.I. maintained active files on the New Haven Black Panther Party through 1977.
The John R. Williams Papers are arranged in two series.
SERIES I, F.B.I. HEADQUARTERS FILES, 1966-1977, consists of photocopied material from the national headquarters of the F.B.I. in Washington, D.C. These files are identified by the number "105-165706-2" And are subdivided into sections. The sections are arranged in numerical order, with each section containing a chronological accumulation of material. One file, labelled "sub A" and arranged at the end of the series, documents press coverage of the Black Panther Party. Files for "June" which consist of logs of telephone conversations, documents defending the use of telephone surveillance, and papers seeking the continuance of wire-tapping through 1972, are also arranged at the end of the series.
SERIES II, NEW HAVEN OFFICE FILES, 1966-1977, consists of photocopied material from the New Haven F.B.I. office. These files are identified by the number "NH100-19186" and are arranged in numerical sections. Each section contains a chronological run of material. Files relating to press coverage are found in files "sub 4" and an alphabetical sequence of files "sub A - sub X" contain copies of evidence seized in raids on party offices following the Alex Rackley murder. A group of files labelled "NH157-1601", arranged at the end of the series, contains information relating to demonstrations, speeches, and rallies.
African Americans -- Civil rights; African Americans -- Politics and suffrage; Attorney and client -- United States; Black militant organizations -- United States; Law enforcement -- United States; May Day (Labor holiday); Privacy, Right of -- United States; Race relations -- United States; Radicals; Trials (Murder) -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Wiretapping -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Connecticut -- Race relations; New Haven (Conn.) -- Race relations; United States -- Social conditions -- 1960-1980; Lawyers; Garry, Charles, 1909-1991; Huggins, Ericka; Kimbro, Warren; McLucas, Lonnie Cleveland, 1945-; Miranda, Doug; Rackley, Alex, d. 1969; Seale, Bobby, 1936-; Williams, John R.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; Black Panther Party; Yale University -- Employees -- Political activity; Yale University -- Students -- Political activity
- F.B.I. Headquarters Files, 1966-1977; Series I; 5 linear feet (11 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material arranged by section number. Material from miscellaneous sections is arranged at the end of the series.
  - File 105-165706-32
    - Sections
      - 1-4, 1968-1969 September (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
      - 4-8, 1969 September-1969 November (Box 2, Folder 9-16)
      - 9-13, 1969 November-1970 March (Box 3, Folder 17-24)
      - 14-18, 1970 March-1970 April (Box 4, Folder 25-31)
      - 18-21, 1970 April-1970 May (Box 5, Folder 32-37)
      - 22-26, 1970 May-1970 July (Box 6, Folder 38-44)
      - 27-31, 1970 July-1970 October (Box 7, Folder 45-51)
      - 31-34, 1970 October-1971 January (Box 8, Folder 52-58)
      - 35-38, 1971 January-1971 June (Box 9, Folder 59-65)
      - 39-42, 1971 June-1975 January (Box 10, Folder 66-70)
      - Sub A, 1969 March-1971 June (Box 10, Folder 71)
      - June, 1969 March-1969 November (Box 10, Folder 72)
      - June, 1969 March-1972 March (Box 11, Folder 73-74)
- F.B.I. New Haven Office Files, 1966-1977; Series II; 9 linear feet (23 boxes)
  This series contains material arranged by file number and then by section number or letter.
  - File NH100-19186
    - Sections
      - 1-6, 1969 February-1969 May (Box 12, Folder 75-81)
      - 7-12, 1968 September-1969 June (Box 13, Folder 82-88)
      - 13-17, 1969 June-1969 August (Box 14, Folder 89-95)
      - 18-27, 1969 August-1969 November (Box 15, Folder 96-102)
      - 28-32, 1969 November-1969 December (Box 16, Folder 103-108)
      - 33-38, 1969 December-1970 January (Box 17, Folder 109-116)
      - 39-44, 1970 February-1970 March (Box 18, Folder 117-123)
      - 44-49, 1969 November-1970 April (Box 19, Folder 124-129)
      - 50-54, 1970 April-1970 May (Box 20, Folder 130-137)
      - 55-60, 1970 May-1970 June (Box 21, Folder 138-145)
      - 6o-64, 1970 June-1970 July (Box 22, Folder 146-153)
      - 65-69, 1970 May-1970 August (Box 23, Folder 154-159)
      - 70-75, 1970 July-1970 August (Box 24, Folder 160-167)
      - 76-81, 1970 October-1971 January (Box 25, Folder 168-174)
      - 82-87, 1971 January-1971 March (Box 26, Folder 175-180)
      - 88-94, 1971 March-1971 June (Box 27, Folder 181-187)
      - 94-98, 1971 July-1971 December (Box 28, Folder 188-192)
      - 99-103, 1972 January-1973 April (Box 29, Folder 193-198)
      - 104-105, 1973 April-1977 October (Box 30, Folder 199-201)
      - sub 4: 1-3, 1967 October-1970 July (Box 31, Folder 202-207)
      - sub 4: 4-8, 1970 April-1973 June (Box 32, Folder 208-213)
      - sub A-P, 1969 May-1970 August (Box 33, Folder 214-229)
      - sub Q-X, 1970 October-1972 January (Box 34, Folder 230-237)
  - File NH157-1601
    - Sections
      - 1-3, 1970 January-1977 January (Box 34, Folder 238-240)